#### **Fatih SAYIN**

Austin, TX 78729 | fmsayin@hotmail.com| (512) 765 3221 | https://www.linkedin.com/in/fatih-sayin

 $GitHub: \underline{https://github.com/fmsayin} \mid Portfolio: \underline{https://fmsayin.github.io}$ 

#### **CAREER SUMMARY**

A strategic, multidisciplinary data analyst with an eye for innovation and analytical perfection. Combining my expertise and research analyst background in this area to deliver the best creative data visualizations and actionable insights with perfect approximation algorithms. Proactively perfect skill sets and deep experience with the tools VBA, Python, Ipython, Pandas, SQL, MongoDB, HTML, CSS, JavaScript, Tableau, Scikit-Learn, and Spark.

### **EDUCATION**

The University of Texas at Austin | Data Analytics and Visualization | 2019 Ivane Javakhishvili State University | Georgia | Ph.D. | 2009

### AREAS OF EXPERTISE

- Data and Quantitative Analysis
- Decision Analytics
- Machine Learning, Predictive Modeling
- Data-Driven Personalization
- Big Data Queries and Interpretation
- Data Mining and Visualization Tools
- Tableau

- Advanced Excel Functions: Pivot Tables, VBA Scripting
- Fundamental Statistics: Modeling, Forecasting
- Programming: Python, Numpy, Pandas, Matplotlib, API Interactions, Social Media Mining
- Databases: SQL, MongoDB
- Research, Reports, and Forecasts
- Web Visualization: HTML, CSS, Bootstrap, Dashboarding, JavaScript, Leaflet.j

# MOST RECENT PROJECTS

# 1. Project

- Name: Trends in Austin Crime Data by Zip Code
- **Description:** The city of Austin provides lots of interesting local data sets. We interested in crime data. Base on the data, zip code was the best geographic measure, but also wanted to use demographic data from the Census. We tried to describe each zip code base on four socio-economic indicators: income level, educational attainment, poverty level, unemployment rate. [Team Project]

Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/GROUP-PROJECT-Trends-in-Austin-crime-data-by-zip-code

**Prezi Link:** <a href="https://prezi.com/view/46V1XovwTPcJulr4D0rN/">https://prezi.com/view/46V1XovwTPcJulr4D0rN/</a> (for project presentation)

### 2. Project

- Name: Machine Learning Real Estate Project (The Relationship between Stock Market & Real Estate Price)
- **Description:** The purpose of this project was to build a real-estate pricing model with a dataset which we gathered from Real Estate Investment Trust (REIT). In this project 8 popular machine learning models were used, such as Decision Tree Regression, Random Forest Regression, K Nearest Neighbors Regression, Support Vector Machine, Ridge Regression, XGBoost, Lasso Regression, Baseline Model. [Team Project]

Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/Machine-Learning-Real-Estate-Project

### 3. Project

- Name: European Soccer League Analysis (EuroLeague)
- **Description:** European Soccer League vs GDP data set was analyzed. The success of teams has positive correlation with the GDP of its country. Each teams scorers and goals data were analyzed. The results were compared with the country and city's GDP. [Team Project]

Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/ETL-Project-EuroLeague

### MOST RECENT ACCOMPLISHMENTS

# 1. Heroes of Pymoli Game Data Analysis

• **Description:** Programmed a general python script to analyze the data for a game. Generated a report that breaks down the game's purchasing data into meaningful insights.

Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/Heroes\_of\_Pymoli

# 2. The World Cities Weather vs Latitude

• **Description:** Coded a weather API python general script for over randomly selected 500 + cities across the world of varying distance from the equator to detect their temperature, humidity, cloudiness, and wind speed based on their latitude.

Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/Weather\_Py

# 3. Rental Movie Database

• **Description:** Formulated a query to program total sales by each store and staff by type of the movies. Most frequently rented movies, top genres of movies that were detected.

Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/mysql\_challange

# 4. New York City Bike Analytics with Tableau

• **Description:** Analyzed New York City Bike Data which is the largest bike sharing program in the US. Aggregated the data to build a data dashboard, story and report with Tableau. Created geo maps, bar-pie-line charts with the aggregated columns in order to determine the insight of the data.

Link: <a href="https://github.com/fmsayin/New-York-City-Bike-Analytics-with-Tableau">https://github.com/fmsayin/New-York-City-Bike-Analytics-with-Tableau</a>

### 5. Kick Start Campaign: The Most Successful Start-Up Projects

• **Description:** Diagnosed and analyzed a database of 4,000 past projects in order to uncover any hidden trends for being a successful or unsuccessful Kick Start Campaign.

Link: <a href="https://github.com/fmsayin/advanced">https://github.com/fmsayin/advanced</a> excel

### 6. Web-Visualization

Jun 2009 – Jul 2011

• **Description:** This is an analysis and visualization of weather of 500+ cities across the world. The main objective was to showcase the relationship of various factors like temperature, humidity, cloudiness and wind speed with respect to the distance from the equator.

**Link:** <a href="https://github.com/fmsayin/Web-Visualization.github.io">https://github.com/fmsayin/Web-Visualization.github.io</a>

	PROFESSIONAL AND ACADEMIC EXPERIENCE
Jan 2019 – Present	Data Analyst, Cosmos Trading Inc. Austin, Texas, USA
	<b>Project Name:</b> Stock Market Analysis between 2018 – 2019
	Description: This project was about, looking at data from particularly stock market
	analysis. In the project, we used pandas to get stock market information, for visualization we used matplotlib, seaborn and beautiful soup and some ways of
	analyzing the risk of a stock.
	Link: <a href="https://github.com/fmsayin/Stock-Market-AnalysisBetween-2018-2019">https://github.com/fmsayin/Stock-Market-AnalysisBetween-2018-2019</a>
Oct 2018 – Apr 2019	Data Analytics and Visualization Boot Camp, The University of Texas at Austin
Aug 2016 – Sep 2018	Freelance Research Analyst, Austin, Texas, USA
Sep 2014 – Jul 2016	Founding Director of Research Center / Research Analyst, Canik Basari University,
	Samsun, Turkey
Sep 2012 – Jul 2016	Assistant Professor, Canik Basari University, Samsun, Turkey

Assistant Professor, International Black Sea University, Tbilisi, Georgia